all right
[Music]
thousands of years ago in ancient Egypt
diabetes was described as a two great
emptying of urine or more poetically as
being like the River Nile between the
thighs the recommended remedy ironically
was a diet consisting of wheat grains
grapes honey and berries
the guy coined the term diabetes about
500 years later also prescribed a high
carbohydrate diet then right up until we
had insulin doctors were saving the
lives of diabetics with an oatmeal diet
this wouldn't make any sense until sir
Harold Hemsworth arrived on the scene
the first to separate out type 1
diabetes from type 2 diabetes and Define
this concept of insulin resistance after
just a few days on a high fat diet you
can get twice the blood sugar spike in
response to drinking sugar water
compared after eating a high carb diet
now that type 2 diabetes is like the
black death of the 21st century in terms
of devastating Health impacts what about
revisiting the almost forgotten
short-term dietary oatmeal intervention
as an economical yet spoiler alert
highly effective tool to achieve better
blood sugar control in patients with
type 2 diabetes basically patients are
offered up to about two and a half cups
oatmeal three times a day as their meals
with nothing but some herbs and maybe
small amounts of raw vegetables just to
mix things up for how long just a couple
days note that's only like a thousand
calories so the result is a hypocaloric
plant-based dietary intervention that's
low in fat in fact no added fat no salt
and excludes animal protein is a few
days of oatmeal really gonna make much
of a difference check out this case
report of an oatmeal intervention for
severe insulin resistance in the ICU
within 48 Hours of admission the patient
developed such severe insulin resistance
she required more than 200 units of
insulin per day up until then the
patient received standard diabetic tube
feeds which obviously were not working
so instead they dropped oatmeal and
vegetables down the tube instead
presumably using a really good blender
and lo and behold it worked but you've
got to see the numbers yeah her first
blood sugars of the day dropped from
around 250 down to about a hundred five
days later but that near normal blood
sugar was on 160 fewer units of insulin
down from over 200 units a day lower
blood sugars on 160 fewer units of
insulin
okay I can see how if you're trying to
save a life in the ICU an oatmeal diet
can be near miraculous but just in
regular diabetics what good is eating
oatmeal for a few days if you just go
back to your regular diet
several studies have suggested that the
beneficial effects could last like a
month after the few days of oatmeal for
example in this randomized controlled
crossover trial not only did insulin
needs drop like 40 percent in just two
days compared to just restricting
calories alone with a hypochloric
diabetic diet a measure of long-term
blood sugar control taken four weeks
later reflected the benefit so we're
talking a highly significant reduction
of required daily insulin doses with
beneficial effects shown Weeks Later who
cares if you have to take huge doses of
insulin though because insulin causes
weight gain which just makes the
underlying insulin resistance worse so
it's like this vicious cycle but instead
with the oatmeal you're actually
treating the cause not to mention the
incidence of cancer and overall
mortality associated with having such
high levels of insulin in your body all
the time
other new Studies have shown the same
thing two days of oatmeal significantly
reducing the required amount of insulin
and improved blood sugar levels with
beneficial effects noted for up to four
weeks for example here patients with
uncontrolled type 2 diabetes with the
two-day oatmeal diet leading to a 40
reduction of insulin dose accompanied
with almost normalization of average
blood sugars although the intervention
only lasted for two days they observed a
lasting significant reduction of insulin
dosage and ameliorated mean blood sugars
for weeks after they were dismissed from
the study and this was after they
resumed their regular diets look at this
massive drop in insulin needs after the
oatmeal for two days but look a month
later they were still needing like 40
less insulin wait a second how could
this short intervention lead to such
dramatic results that somehow continue
on for weeks although short-term dietary
oatmeal interventions cannot be compared
to Whole Food plant-based diets in terms
of maximizing the intake of protective
Foods I mean that's ideally what people
should try to eat to reverse their type
2 diabetes completely but they both
strictly exclude the animal-based foods
that seem to increase the risk of
developing diabetes so even cutting out
saturated fat for like two days May so
reduce insulin resistance you can free
ride on that for at least a few weeks
even if you go back to eating crap
warning though if you try this oatmeal
diet your physician has to be ready to
rapidly deprescribe your blood sugar
drugs else you become dangerously over
medicated I mean imagine if this woman
was still getting 200 units of insulin
her sugars would crash so low she'd be
dead
so oatmeal intervention should not be
performed in patients that might have
difficulties in reporting symptoms of
low blood sugars who you can't closely
monitor so the downside of trying
oatmeal days is that it may work a
little too well so it must be done under
close medical supervision
[Music]
thank you